<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A treatise of the sin against the holy ghost made by M. Augustine Marlorate. Translated out of French to the great consolation of all such as repent them of their sinnes, and to the astonying of of [sic] those that mock and despise the gospell of our Lord Jesus Christ</title>
            <title>Traité du péché contre le Saint Esprit. English.</title>
            <author>Marlorat, Augustin, 1506-1562.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1570</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 55 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A06990</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17410</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S102682</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838453</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838453</idno>
            <idno type="VID">2833</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A06990)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2833)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 815:04)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A treatise of the sin against the holy ghost made by M. Augustine Marlorate. Translated out of French to the great consolation of all such as repent them of their sinnes, and to the astonying of of [sic] those that mock and despise the gospell of our Lord Jesus Christ</title>
                  <title>Traité du péché contre le Saint Esprit. English.</title>
                  <author>Marlorat, Augustin, 1506-1562.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[40] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By [J. Allde for] Lucas Harison,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1570?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of: Marlorat, Augustin. Traité du péché contre le Saint Esprit.</note>
                  <note>Allde's name from colophon; publication date conjectured by STC.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: Of the sin against the holy ghost.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B C⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sin, Unpardonable --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:2833:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2833:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A TREATISE</hi> of the ſin againſt the holy ghoſt <hi>made by M. Auguſtine</hi> Marlorate. Tranſlated out of french <hi>to the great conſolation of</hi> all ſuch as repent them of their ſinnes, <hi>and to the aſtonying of</hi> of thoſe that mock and deſpiſe the Goſpell of our Lord Ieſus Chriſte.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Iames. 5. verſe. 19.20.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>¶Breethern if any of you haue erred from the trueth and ſome man hath conuerted him / let him knowe that he whiche hath conuerted the ſinner from going aſtray out of his way / ſhal ſaue a ſoule fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> death and ſhall hide a multitude of ſinnes.</p>
            </q>
            <p>¶ <hi>Imprinted at London by Lucas Hariſon</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:2833:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2833:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Augustine Marlorate to</hi> the chriſtian Reader wiſſheth health and peace through Ieſus Chriſte.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Eſt any should think</hi> that in this ſmall Treatiſe, I (like an euill Attorney) would go about to defend the cauſe of ſuche, as mocking God, do dally with the Goſpel thincking to fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low it or leaue it as oft as they liſt, as if of them ſelues &amp; at their ovvne choiſe they might make atonement vvith the ſonne of God, vvhom they giue ouer to opprobry: I beſeeche you in the name of our Lord Ieſus patie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly to reed ouer this Treatiſe to the end.</p>
            <p>So dooing I hope ye vvil iudge that mine intent heerby is onely to bring ſuch again into the right vvay of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as hetherto haue not ſo vvel pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fited in the knovvledge of the Goſpel that ineſtimable treaſure as the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency and great benefit thereof re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth: to th'end that all ſuch as shall heerafter hear the ſound of the voice of Ieſus Chriſte in his Churche, may knovve that he is redy to iudge ſuche as reſiſt &amp; diſpiſe his vvord, but cheef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:2833:3"/>thoſe that in this great light of the Goſpel<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ephe.</hi>
4.29</note> gree<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e the holy ſpirit of God by vvhome the faithfull are ſealed for the day of their redemption.</p>
            <p>Foraſmuch then as the vvord of God is directed to diuers maner of people, and is not receiued of all vvith one ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ner affection, as appeereth in the ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litude of the ſeed,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.19.</note> this Treatiſe may ſerue to bothe, that the good (being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired with the holy ghoſt) may be aſſu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red of the doctrin vvhich they folow and may be ſtrengthned more &amp; more in the Lord, and in the povver of his might,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ephe.</hi> 6.10. <hi>Galla.</hi> 1.8.</note> couragiouſly to reiect all ſpirits (yea vvere it an angel of Heauen) that should teach any other doctrin for the ſaluation of men then that vvhiche is contained in the holy goſpel: and that ſuch other as this holy and ſacred do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrin hath not yet take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo deep root in, may erneſtly bee moued to conſider at the le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth vvherin the ſuretie of their ſaluation co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiſteth,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ephe.</hi> 4.14</note> that they fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hence foorth be no more like children waue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring &amp; caried about with euery winde of doctrin, by the deceit of men &amp; by craftines, whereby they lye in waite to deceiue: But vvholly may reſt on
<pb facs="tcp:2833:3"/>Chriſte and ſubmit them ſelues to him vvhich died &amp; is riſen again for them:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom</hi> 14.9.</note> and alſo to the end that they vvhiche through infirmitie, or for fear of men, or loſſe of their goods &amp; honors haue shut vp and hidden the ſecret of faith, may vvake out of their drouſy forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes &amp; heerafter open their mouthes to confeſſe to ſaluation before all men that vvhich fait harted fear hath made them ſo long to hide &amp; diſſemble,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.10.</note> leaſt preferring the glory of men before the glory of God, they in th'end feel the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ffect &amp; executio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of this horrible threa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning vvhich is pronou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ced on the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that tempt Ieſus Chriſt before men Finally this treatiſe tendeth to this end that all excuſes ſet apart,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.33. <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.12. <hi>Act.</hi> 17.30. <hi>Mal.</hi>
4.6.</note> eche ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may ſeek for his ſaluation vvith fear &amp; trembling, ſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing that God hauing ſo lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g forborn in time of ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, vvilleth novv al men in all places to repent, leſt he come and ſtrike the earth to deſtruction.</p>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Ezech. <hi>18.27.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>VVhen the wicked turneth away from his wickednes that he hath committed &amp; doth that which is lawfull and right hee ſhall ſaue his ſoule aliue.</p>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Hebru. <hi>4.16.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Let vs go boldely vnto the throne of grace that we may receiue mercy and finde grace in time of need.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:2833:4"/>
            <head>A treatiſe of the ſin againſt <hi>the holy Ghoſt.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Eeing that bolde</hi> and raſh men ouerſhoot them ſelues ſo far, as to giue iudgement of that which is knowen to one onely God, and oft for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getting what they them ſelues ought to be, and how they ought to liue according to Gods will, cruelly condemne thoſe on whome the Lord wil haue mercy: It is good firſt to note that not all ſin which ſéemeth to be againſt the holy Ghoſt, is ſin againſt the holy Ghoſt in deed: for there are many that reſiſt the trueth of the Goſpel, wherof if ſéemeth they haue had ſome knowledge, whiche neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe ſin not againſt the holy Ghoſt, in as much as it is ioyned with ſome ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce which exempteth them from this horri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſin whiche is not pardoned in this world,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 12.3.</note> nor in the world to come. Which <hi>S. Paule</hi> ſignifieth,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.13.</note> ſaying: that he obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned pardon, becauſe that through igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance and for lack of faith he had béen a blaſphemer, a perſecutor and oppreſſor: wherby it foloweth that not all ſin (wher
<pb facs="tcp:2833:4"/>with man reſiſteth the trueth of God) is ſin againſt the holy Ghoſt.</p>
            <p>But when man is ſo touched with the light of the troth, that he cannot pretend ignorance, and neuertheleſſe of determi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nate malice reſiſteth, then he ſinneth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the holy Ghoſt, and it is not poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for him to be renued by repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tance, in that he hath forſaken God and is becom an Apoſtata or forſaker of Chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. Such were the Scribes and Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeyes, who hauing the knowledge of the Law,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 9.34.
<hi>&amp;.</hi> 12.24.</note> and ſeeing the manifeſt woorks of the power of God, attributed the mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles which Ieſus Chriſt wrought, to <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zebub.</hi> Such were they alſo which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted S. Stephen, and of determinate purpoſe blamed that doctrin, wherof they could not be ignorant but that it procée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded from God: as that holy Martir like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe reprooued them, when he was redy to ſhed his blood in the defence of the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrin of the Ghoſpel. For if S. Stephen had delt with ignorant men, hee would haue vſed them otherwiſe. But ſeeing that they raged againſt God, and went about to rob God of his honor, he boldely pronounceth that they withſtand the ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt, let vs the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> conclude that they ſin
<pb facs="tcp:2833:5"/>againſt the holy Ghoſt, who hauing the knowledge of God trueth, doo neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leſſe of determinat malice reſiſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame.</p>
            <p>But let vs ſée whether it be lawful to pray for thoſe that are giltye of this ſin, for it ſéemeth no, by many reaſons.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Mat, 21.22 Mar. 11.24 Iam. 1.6.</note>Firſt the prayer of the faithfull ought to be made in faith, which béeing grounded on the woord of God, we are aſſured that they ſhalbe heard. And ther is no word of God y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> aſſureth vs that our prayer ſhalbe heard for thoſe that ſin againſt the holy ghoſt, but rather if ſaith co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary wiſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> there is a ſin to death and I ſay not ſaith S. Iohn, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou ſhalt pray for ſuch. It folo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>weth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that it is in vain for vs to pray for thoſe that ſin againſt the holy Ghoſt.<note place="margin">1. Ioh. 5.16</note>
            </p>
            <p>Further Th'apoſtle ſaith plainly that ſuche cannot be renued by repentaunce ſeeing they crucifie againe to them ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues the Son of God and make a mock of him.<note place="margin">Heb. 6
6.</note> If it be impoſſible y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they can be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted, and the end of our prayers is that ſinners may amend, it ſeemeth ſuperflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to pray for their conuerſion.</p>
            <p>Further we cannot obtain forgiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of ſinnes, but onely by the ſatiſfacti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on of our Sauiour Ieſus Chriſte,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ephe.</hi> 5.2.</note> who hath offred vp him ſelf to bee an offring and ſacrifice of a ſweet ſmelling ſauor to God. Then if we ſin willingly after we
<pb facs="tcp:2833:5"/>haue had the knowledge of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> troth, there remaineth no more ſacrifice for ſinnes:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.26.</note> but a fearful looking for iudgement, and violent fire which ſhall deuoure the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaries. If the blood of Ieſus Chriſte ſhed for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> faithful profiteth not the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that ſin againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy Ghoſt, it foloweh that all prayers made for them auaile them nothing, for that they are cut of from the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munion of Ieſus Chriſt, out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which there is no hope of ſaluation or pardon.</p>
            <p>The example of S. Paule ſeemeth al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firme y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame which writeth thꝰ.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 4.14</note> 
               <hi>Alexander</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> copper ſmith hath doon me much euil the Lord rewarde him accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his works.<note place="margin">2. <hi>C i.</hi> 4.14.</note> If S. Paule had kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen that prayer would haue profited <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lexander,</hi> I dout not but he would haue prayed for his conuerſion: but ſéeing hee ſo hainouſly reſiſted the doctrin of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel wherof he once made profeſſion, as it is likely by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which S. Luke writeth,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 29.33.</note> he leaneth him as deſperat, yea and wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth that God would puniſh him accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his deſerts We might alſo al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge how God hath forbide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts to pray for the wicked: as whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſaith to Ieremy.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iere.</hi> 11.14. <hi>Iere.</hi> 11.11.</note> Therfore thou ſhalt not pray for this people, neither lift vp a cry or prayer for them for when they cry
<pb facs="tcp:2833:6"/>vnto me in their trouble I wil not hear them. And again, thou ſhalt not pray to doo this people good. Further the Lord ſaith to Samuel. How long wilt thou morne for Saule,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 16.1</note> ſéeing I haue caſt him away from reigning any more ouer Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael.</p>
            <p>Finally, it ſéemeth that the curſſes which the Prophets vſe againſt the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked &amp; reprobate, declare that we ought not to pray vnto God for their amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but rather for their ouerthrowe and confuſion. As when Dauid ſaith: Stand vp Lord for my help,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſa.</hi> 35.2.3 4.5.6.</note> bring out al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſo the Speare, and ſtop the way againſt them that perſecute me, ſay vnto my ſoule, I am thy ſaluation. Let them be confounded and put to ſhame that ſéeke after my ſoule, let them be turned back and brought to confuſion that imagine mine hurt. Let them be as chaffe before the winde, and let the Angel of the Lord ſcatter them. Let their way be dark and ſlippery, and let the Angel of the Lord purſue them.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſa.</hi> 40.14</note> Alſo: Let them be confoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and put to ſhame togither that ſéek my ſoule to deſtroy it, let them be driuen backward and put to rebuke that deſire mine hurt.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi>
55.15.</note> Alſo: Let death ſeaſe vpon
<pb facs="tcp:2833:6"/>them, let them go down quick into the graue, for wickednes is in their dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> midſt of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Alſo: Breke their téeth (O God) in their mouthes:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 58.6.7.8.</note> Break the iawes of the yung Lions, O Lord. Let them melt like the waters, let them paſſe away: when he ſhooteth his Arrowes let them be as broken. Let him conſume like a Snail that melteth and like the vntimely frute of a woman that hath not ſéen the Sun. Alſo, euen thou O Lord God of hoſts,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 59.5.13.</note> God of Iſrael awake to viſit al the heathen, and be not merciful vnto all that traſgreſſe malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly. Conſume them in thy wrath, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume them that they be no more.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 69.22.23.</note> And again: Let their table be a ſnare before them, and let their proſperitie be made their ouerthrowe. Let their eyes be blin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded that they ſee not, and make their Raines continually to treemble. Poure foorth thine indignation vpon them, and let thy wrathful diſpleaſure ſeaſe vpon them. Alſo:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 71.13.</note> Let them be confou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded and conſumed that are againſt my ſoule, let them be couered with reproofe &amp; confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſéek mine hurt. Further:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 74.3.</note> Lift vp thy ſtrokes that thou maiſt for euer deſtroy euery enemy that doth euil to thy ſanctu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ary
<pb facs="tcp:2833:7"/>Alſo: Poure out thy wrath vpon the heathen that haue not knowen thee,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 79.6.11.</note> and vpon the kingdoms that haue not called vpon thy name. And render vnto our neighours ſeuen folde into their boſom their reproch, wherwith they haue repro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ched thée O Lord. Further: Doo thou to them as vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <hi>Midianits,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 83.9.13.14.15.16.17.</note> as to <hi>Siſera</hi> and as to
<hi>labin</hi> at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> riuer of <hi>Kisho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> And anon after: O my God make the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> like vnto a whéel, &amp; as the ſtuble before the winde, as the fire burneth the foreſt and as the flames ſetteth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mountains on fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, ſo perſecute them w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the tempeſt and make them afraid with thy ſtorme. Fil their faces with ſhame y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they may ſéek thy name O Lord. Let them be confoun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded &amp; trouble for euer, yea let them be put to ſhame and periſh. Alſo: Set thou the wicked ouer him and let the aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary ſtand at his right hand.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi>
109.6.14.</note> Let the ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity of his father be had in reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brance with the Lord, and let not the ſin of his mother be doon away. Alſo: As for the cheef of them that compaſſe me about,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 140.9 10.</note> let the miſchéef of their owne lips come vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them. Let coles fall vpon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, let him caſt them into the fire, and into the deep pits that they riſe not. Theſe and ſuch
<pb facs="tcp:2833:7"/>like places as well of the Pſalmes as of the Prophets ſéem to make for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that wil not haue vs pray for the wicked and cheefly thoſe that wage battail againſt the doctrin of the Goſpel, but rather they ſay that by the example of Dauid and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers we ſhuld pray to God for their o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrow and deſtruction, as wel to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunce his glory, as to kéep the good in fear, leſt they ioine them ſelues with the reprobate.</p>
            <p>But before we anſwere to theſe ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iections, and to all the places before al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leged, which ſeem to confirme their oppi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, we would faine demaund of them whether they be ſure that thoſe whome they condemne, are gilty of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſin againſt the holy Ghoſt, they &amp; thoſe from whom they ſhut vp the way of ſaluation be ſuch as the Author of the Epiſtle to the
<hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brues</hi> deſcribeth? that is to ſay,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.4.</note> whether they were once lightned, whether they haue taſted the Heauenly gift and whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they were made partakers of the holy Ghoſt, whether they haue taſted of the good woord of God, and the powers of the world to come? For the Apoſtle ſet<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teth foorth all theſe things before he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounceth ſentence againſt thoſe that
<pb facs="tcp:2833:8"/>ſo hainouſly offend that they can not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain pardon, to th'end that wee ſhould knowe that all departing from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> troth of the Ghoſpel or perſecuting therof, is not an vnforgiuenable ſin: els we muſt néeds ſay that S. Péeter ſinned againſt the holy Ghoſt,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.74</note> ſéeing he renounced (yea and that with curſing and hanning) the troth whiche he him ſelf had before kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen and confeſſed. And yet he that ſhall ſo iudge muſt néeds be blamed of raſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and vntroth,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.16. <hi>Iohn.</hi> 6.69.</note> aſwel becauſe of the<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.75</note> repentance of this Diſciple, as of the pardon which he obtained, of his maſter and Lord. And if any wil ſay that there ar diuers ſuch as the Apoſtle deſcribeth, euen as we wil not deny it, for aſmuche as theſe things are not written for nought, and that Ieſus Chriſt wold not haue made ſo expreſſe mention of the ſin againſt the holy Ghoſt, if there had not béen ſuch a ſin, ſo likewiſe we ſay it is not ſo eaſy to be knowen as it ſéemeth: and it is much better to ſuſpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d our iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in this caſe and to leaue the know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ledge therof to god<note n="*" place="margin">2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.14.</note> who knoweth thoſe that be his, then lightly and raſhly to condemne thoſe that poſſibly God hath determined to ſhew mercy vnto, that
<pb facs="tcp:2833:8"/>the more horrible the ſin ſéemeth and void of all pardon, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> more he might mag<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nifie his great goodneſſe and mercy. For it often commeth to paſſe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.20.</note> that where ſin hath abounded, there grace aboundeth much more. Beſide this, the faith which we haue in the promiſes of God, whiche promiſeth pardon to all thoſe that repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t them from the bottom of their harts,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezech.</hi>
18.23</note> and the charitie which we bere to our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor prouoketh vs to hope wel of all men, and to pray to God for the ſaluation of all ſinners: euen of thoſe that ſéem to be the moſte deſperate in the world. Alſo what ſhall we ſay by this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that Chriſt gaue to his diſciples, ſaying: Loue your enmies,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi>
5.44.</note> bleſſe thoſe that curſe you, doo good to thoſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hate you, pray for thoſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hurt you &amp; perſecute you, that ye may be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> children of your father which is in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: for he maketh his Sun to ſhine vpon the good and bad, and ſendeth his rain vpon the iuſt and vniuſt. And S. Paule ſaith: The ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord muſt not ſtriue,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.24 25.26.</note> but muſt bee gentle towards all men, apt to teach, ſuffering the euil men patiently, inſtructing them with méekneſſe that are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary minded, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing if God at any time wil giue them
<pb facs="tcp:2833:9"/>repentance that they may knowe the troth, and that they may come to amend<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment out of the ſnare of the Deuil, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che are taken of him at his wil. In deed the Apoſtle ſpeaketh not directly of thoſe that reſiſt the troth that they once knew neither yet excludeth he thoſe which are ſuch, becauſe God is able inough to call them again to the true knowledge of the troth, and to giue them that taſte of Hea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uenly and deuine things whiche before they had loſt. Seeing then that we know not how God wil woork with men, and that the conuerſion of ſinners is in his hand, and that we are not ſure whether they whiche reſiſt the troth to day ſhall conſent to morrow, or whether they be miſled by ignorance, wekeneſſe, or any fond zeale, we cannot doo amiſſe to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend them to God, and to pray for their conuerſion and amendment.</p>
            <p>Touching the anſwers and ſolutions of the former obiections, we firſt confeſſe that all our prayers ought to be made in faith: without the which, man may not look to obtain any thing at Gods hand as S. Iames ſaith: We confeſſe alſo that the woord of God commaundeth vs not to pray for theſe that ſin againſt the holy<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iames.</hi> 1.7</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:2833:9"/>Ghoſt: But therwith we ſay that it is not eaſy for vs to knowe ſuch ſinners, as appée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth by the reaſons before alleged. For they ſomtimes ar thought to ſin maliciouſly and of determinate purpoſe, that are rather mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſled with fond zeale and blinde ignorance then of determinate malice. It may ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, come to paſſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that amongſt thoſe that perſecute the Goſpel, ſome ſin of igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance and other ſome of malice, and ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently againſt the holy Ghoſt. But for that the intent of the hart is reſerued to the knowledge of God alone, the faithful ought ſtil to pray for all in generall. As we ſée S. Stephen did.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 7.51.6<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> For though they were of his aduerſaries y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> reſiſted the holly Ghoſt, as he laid to their charge, yet when he was redy to yéeld vp the Ghoſt, he ceaſſed not to pray in generall, without exception of this man or that man, ſaying, Lord lay not this ſin to their charge, for they knowe not what they doo. And in déed if we ſhould iudge who ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned againſt the holy Ghoſt in perſecuting this holy man, ſhould we not put Saule in the number of them at the leaſt? For from his youth he had béen inſtructed in the law vnder that excellent doctor <hi>Gamaliel:</hi> and could wel iudge that all that S. Steuen al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leged for the defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of his doctrin, was draw<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>en out of the pure fountain of the holy ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures:
<pb facs="tcp:2833:10"/>and neuertheleſſe his ſudain &amp; won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful conuerſion, dooth ſufficiently declare that his ſin was not vnpardonable, as hee him ſelf dooth ſufficiently witneſſe.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.10 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.16</note> Alſo we ſée many y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>, ſéemed to be wholly caſt away and deſperat which neuertheleſſe are ſo tou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ched with the féeling of their ſinnes, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they erneſtly repent, &amp; are ſet foorth to others as mirrors &amp; examples of the goodneſſe of God which giueth life to the dead, and calleth the things y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> be not as though they were. The example of the Corinthians and Galathi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans may ſerue to this purpoſe very wel,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.17.</note> for ſome of them were ſo far departed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that pure doctrin y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> S. Paule had preached vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that they douted of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reſurrection of the dead, theſe were ſtrayed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chriſt, (which had called the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> through grace to an other goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel) ſo far that they thought the ceremonies of the law were neceſſary to ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.35. <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.6.</note> wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they not only gainſaid y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> doctrin of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, but alſo like mad men bereued them ſelues of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> frute that all the faithful haue by the death of Ieſꝰ Chriſt:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.1.</note> &amp; neuertheleſſe the holy Apoſtle leaueth not to indeuer to bring the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> bothe again into the right way of troth.</p>
            <p>For the ſin againſt the holy Ghoſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porteth not ſimply ſome euil or falſe opinion that one may holde againſt ſome or many points of Religion, but a generall reuol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb facs="tcp:2833:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>and apoſtaſie from all Chriſtianitie, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hauing béen illuminate by the vertue of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy Ghoſt, reſiſteth of determinate ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lice the doctrin of the trueth, with intent to reſiſt it. And it is no maruail if this ſin be vnpardonable, ſéeing y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he which is is giltie of them, maliciouſly deſpiſeth Ieſus Chriſt, and maketh a mock of his doctrin, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out the which none can obtain pardon of his iniqui<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ties, and we may not think it ſtraunge and accuſe God of crueltie, though he pardo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not ſuch ſin, ſéeing y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they which co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit it co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e not to repentance. And is it reaſon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> God ſhuld pardon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſin that the offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der nothing repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth? This is it that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Apoſtle affirmeth ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: If we ſin willingly after y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued the knowledge of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> trueth,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.26.</note> there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth no more ſacrifice for ſinnes, that is to ſay If we wittingly and obſtinatly leaue of the doctrin of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Goſpel which teacheth vs that Ieſus Chriſte hath giuen him ſelf to clenſe vs from all our ſinnes,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tits.</hi> 2.14.</note> there reſteth no more ſacrifice for our ſinnes. For there is nothing but the blood of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſonne of God that can clenſe vs from our ſinnes that we haue committed againſt God.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 1.7.</note> Touching that which is alleaged of <hi>Alexander</hi> the copper ſmith,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> it is not to be douted but S. Paule who was ful of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy ghoſt, had ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e perticu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler reuelatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; knowledge of certain perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s
<pb facs="tcp:2833:11"/>with whome he had to doo, by vertue of the which holy Ghoſt, hee did diſcloſe their wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe and hipocriſie and holdely deteſts it before all men, which gift is not giuen to all men, neither is it neceſſary: for Gods wil is to keep vs within the bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds of ſobri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etie and modeſtie. And it is good reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that we leaue to him the knowledge of ſuch high matters, which belong to his vnſearchable and eternall councel. Foraſmuch then as
<hi>Alexander</hi> of determinat<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> purpoſe did fight againſt the troth whiche hee knew,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16.22.</note> Saint Paule pronounceth that ſuch wickedneſſe is altogither vnworthy of mercy. Like<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wiſe he ſaith in an other place: If any man looue not the Lord Ieſus Chriſt, let him be excommunicate to death. And again: He that troubleth you ſhall beare his condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation who ſo euer he be.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi>
5.10.12</note> And anon after: Would to God they were euen cut of whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che doo diſquiet you. But hee that ſhould imitate the holy Apoſtle héerin, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce ſentence of curſſe againſt thoſe that obey not the Goſpel, yea or thoſe that mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly reſiſt the ſame, it is to be feared leſt that whiche the Lord ſaid to his diſciples, might rightly be ſaid vnto him: Ye knowe not of what ſpirit ye are.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luc.</hi>
9.55.</note>
            </p>
            <p>That which is alleaged of Ieremy and Samuel confirmeth that whiche we haue
<pb facs="tcp:2833:11"/>ſaid: that is. If any man haue certain reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation or commaundement not to pray for thoſe that God hath forſaken, we ought to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey it: For then the Lord ſhould manifeſtly declare that ſuch were out of hope of ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. But when we haue no ſuch reuelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, leauing it altogither into the hands of the Lord, we ought of charitie to commit to him the ſaluation of all men: yea and the more hainouſly we ſe them ſin and approch to their ouerthrowe, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> more erneſtly ought we to commend them to God, who killeth and maketh aliue, bringeth downe to the graue and raiſeth vp again,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.6</note> which S Iude commaundeth ſaying: Haue compaſſion of ſome in putting difference,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iude.</hi> 1.22.</note> and others ſaue with feare pulling them out of the fire. S. Peeter ſawe that Simon the Sorcerer was a wicked and ambitious hipocrite, ready to miſuſe and prophane holy and ſpirituall things, and yet after he had ſharply reproo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued him and ſhewed him the iuſt iudgment of God, he mooueth him to repentance, and putteth him in hope of obtayning pardon, ſaying: Repent of thy wickedneſſe and pray to God that if it be poſſible the thought of thine hart may be forgiuen thée:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi>
8.12.</note> for I ſée thou art in the Gall of bitterneſſe and in the band of iniquitie. S. Paule alſo hauing to do with <hi>Elimas</hi> the enchanter that went about<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 13.9.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:2833:12"/>to turn away the deputie from the faith, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced not vnto him the extreme ſeueri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the iudgement of God, but onely after he had declared vnto him his iniquitie, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounceth that hee ſhalbe blinde and not ſée the Sun for a time to th'end that the Depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie ſeeing the vertue of God, which wrought in his holy Apoſtle, might be prouoked to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> doctrin of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goſpel which he brought vnto him. Although then y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> the wicked ſhew ſometimes ſuch euident ſignes of their wic<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kedneſſe and rebellion, that they ſeem whol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly caſt of &amp; deſperate, neuertheleſſe it is not lawful for vs while they are in this preſent life to think y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> they are ſo far out of the way of ſaluation, but that they may be brought home again through the mercy of him that came into this world to ſaue ſinners.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.15</note> As for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> curſes drawen out of diuers Pſalmes, where Dauid craueth Gods help agaiſt his enemyes, deſiring that they may bee ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwen and confou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded, we ſay as we haue ſaid touching that which S. Paule writeth of <hi>Alexander</hi> the copper ſmith that is: that Dauid hauing the ſpirit of prophecie, might haue certain reuelation of the ouerthrowe of thoſe againſt whome he prayed and gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by the ſame ſpirit, he forſheweth and wiſheth (in conforming him ſelf to the iuſt iudgement of God) that his enemyes ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:2833:12"/>come to ſhame and confuſion: Conſidering alſo that this Prophet repreſented the head of the Church, that is to ſay Ieſus Chriſte,<note place="margin">Dauid y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſte</note> King of Kings and onely hed of the faithful: And in this reſpect he boldly proceedeth and ſaith: that all they that withſtand him whome God hath raiſed vp abooue others, ſhalbe ſharply puniſhed for their boldeneſſe and raſhneſſe for that they with ſtand God and his Chriſte. We may not then defend our ſelues with ſuche like curſings as are found in many places of Scriptures, ſeeing there are certain things perticuler to Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, which cannot conſequently belong to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that are much inferior to ſuch holy per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonages: which did as it were foreſee their ouerthrowe at hand, whome they wiſhed to be ſaued if they would haue repented: As appéereth plainly by certain examples of the Scriptures. Moiſes was the mildeſt and gentleſt man that euer was, yet ſeeing the hard and ambitious harts of
<hi>Dathan, Core,</hi> and <hi>Abiron,</hi> and that God was redy to take horrible vengeance on them for their murmuring, ſaid vnto the Lord not with deſire of vengeance, but in the ſpirit of Propheſie. Look not vnto their offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> I haue not taken ſo muche as one Aſſe from them, neither haue I hurte
<pb facs="tcp:2833:13"/>any of them. Yet neuertheleſſe we ſée el<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wher, how erneſtly he laboureth to appeaſe the Lords wrath,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exo.</hi> 32.11</note> whiche ſeemed to bee ſo kindled againſt the people for worſhipping the golden Calf, as though he wold vtterly deſtroy them, who would not thinck that there were two diuers Spirits in this one perſon that he delt more gently with the I dolaters then with the murmurers? Yea it might ſée me that hee was more careful for his owne honor, then of the glory of God, ſith he prayed to the Lord ſo erneſtly to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don the people their Idolatry, as to deſire that the Lord ſhould rather wipe him out of the Book of life, on the other ſide he pray<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eth God not to receiue their offrings which preſumptuouſly ſtood vp againſt him &amp; his brother Aaron, whiche were but mortall men. But the ſame ſpirit which enforced them to craue pardon for the people, prouo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked them to aſke vengeance on the rebells and murmurers which withſtood not onely Moſes and Aaron, but the Lord, vnder whom they exerciſed the charge, which they had receiued of him. The like we ſee in the Apoſtle S. Paule,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.3</note> who did beare ſo great a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ffection to the blinde Iewes that gain ſaid the Ghoſpel, that he deſired to bee ſeperate from Chriſte for their ſaluation, and neuer theleſſe whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he conſidereth how deteſtable
<pb facs="tcp:2833:13"/>their infidelitie &amp; obſtinacy is before God, he boldely pronounceth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> they ſhall feel his horrible vengance. For theſe be his woordꝭ. Who bothe killed the Lord Ieſus and their owne prophets, and haue perſecuted vs,<note place="margin">2.
<hi>Theſſa.</hi> 2.15.16.</note> and God they pleaſe not, and are enemyes to all men: and forbid vs to preach vnto the Gentils that they might be ſaued, to fulfil their ſinnes alwais: for the wrath of God is come on them to the vtmoſt. Séemeth it not héer that hee had forgotten that fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent affection that he bare to his owne na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? But we muſt alwaies come back to that which we before ſaid, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy ghoſt ſo gouerneth the prophetꝭ and apoſtles, that according to y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> knowledge which they haue of the ſecret &amp; iuſt iudgments of God, they haue ſo framed their prayers and requeſts conforming them ſelues thervnto, that not withſtanding they haue not left (as muche as in them lay) to ſue for the ſaluation of poor ſinners, knowi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g that the mercy of God dooth farre ſurmount the rigor of his iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Wherfore let vs boldely condemne, all thoſe that woork iniquitie, &amp; declare vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the rebellious and wicked the iuſt ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance which is prepared for them except they repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. Eſpetially hate the horrible and curſed Apoſtaſie of ſuch as forſake the profe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſion of the Ghoſpel. But let vs beware
<pb facs="tcp:2833:14"/>we enter not to curiouſly into the ſecrets of God, in condemning this man or that man, but rather ſeek by all meanes poſſible, and namely by feruent and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinuall prayer the ſaluation of ſuch as are ſo blinde and miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable that they ſéem willingly to caſt them ſelues away.</p>
            <p>Let vs conſider that the Lord hath at all times ſo magnified his kindeneſſe &amp; mercy towards poor ſinners, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> they whiche ſeemed the moſte wicked &amp; deſperate in the world, haue in th'end béen brought to repentance, and ſo obtained forgiuenes of their offences againſt God. For example, who wold euer haue thought that <hi>Manaſſes</hi> King of Iuda, could haue repented, &amp; that God would haue forgiuen him his ſinnes?<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Chron.</hi> 33. 2.3.4.6.9.</note> The Scripture witneſſeth of him, that he did euil in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſight of the Lord, like the abhominatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, and hee went back and built the high places which <hi>Heſechiah</hi> his father had bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken down, and he ſet vp alters for <hi>Baalim,</hi> and made Groues, and worſhipped all the hoſte of Heauen &amp; ſerued them. He built Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters in the houſe of the Lord. He cauſed his Sonnes to paſſe the fire in the valey of <hi>Ben hinnom.</hi> He gaue him ſelf to Witchcraft and Charming, and Sorcery, and hee vſed them that had familiare ſpirits, and South-ſayers, he did very much euil in the ſight of
<pb facs="tcp:2833:14"/>the Lord to angre him, he made <hi>Iudah</hi> and the inhabitants of
<hi>Ieruſalem</hi> to erre, and to doo wurſſe then the Heathen whome the Lord had deſtroyed before the Children of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> Beſides this he ſhed ſo much inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent blood that he filled <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> from one end to an other,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Kin.</hi>
21.16</note> beſides his ſin wherwith he made <hi>Iudah</hi> to ſin, and to doo euill in the ſight of the Lord. Was there euer King on Earth further from equitie, humanitie and vertue, yea from true Religion<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> wherin he had been inſtructed, not onely becauſe hee was a <hi>Ievv,</hi> but alſo the Sonne of a very good father, which was <hi>Ezechias</hi> that reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the true ſeruice of God? Neuertheleſſe the holy Scripture witneſſeth, that this King <hi>Manaſſes,</hi> ſo wicked, ſo cruel, and ſuch an enemy of true Religion, that he ſée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med rather a Monſter the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a man, beeing in tribulation praied to the Lord his God,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Chr.</hi> 33.12</note> and humbled him ſelf greatly before the God of his Fathers, and prayed vnto him and God was entreated of him, and heard his prayers and brought him again into <hi>Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem,</hi> into his kingdome.</p>
            <p>And euen as he had cauſed the people to turn from the Lord with Idolatrye, ſo com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maunded he
<hi>Iudah</hi> to ſerue the Lord God of <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Lo héer an excellent mirrour of the grace
<pb facs="tcp:2833:15"/>and looue of God towards ſinners that men may learne modeſtie to keep within their bounds, and not raſhly to iudge of the end of any. And therfore S. Paule ſaid of him ſelf. For this cauſe was I receiued to mercy, that Ieſus Chriſte ſhould ſhewe on mee all long ſuffering, to the enſample of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which ſhall in time to come beleeue in him vnto e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall life. Then, euen as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> election of the good and reprobation of the wicked, belong<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eth ſo to the ſecret councel of God, that it were raſhneſſe in man to pronounce any thing abſolutely, but as far as we may ſée by outwarde ſhewes, whiche often times chaunge contrary to our opinion before con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued. So we ſay that as touching y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſin to death or againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy Ghoſt, we may giue no ſudain iudgement leſt experience it ſelf, and the conuerſion and amendme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of thoſe whom we condemne, conuince vs of raſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and folly, yet if we ſhould néeds iudge of the election of the faithful, or reprobation of the wicked, it is muche better ſimply to iudge of the perſeuerance of thoſe in whom we ſée ſome tokens of the election, then of the ouerthrow and vtter deſtruction of ſuch as haue ſome tokens of reprobation.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Cor.</hi>
13.7.</note> For charitie bindeth vs to hope well of thoſe whom God in mercy may bring to repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, ſeeing we ſee that he dayly woorketh
<pb facs="tcp:2833:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>contrary to mans expectation.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.6.</note> S. Paule ſaith, that he is perſwaded that he that hath begun, a good woork in the Phillippians, wil performe it vntil y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> day of Ieſus Chriſt: and addeth that it beco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth him ſo to iudge of them all. He ſaith alſo to the Theſſaloni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> ye are all Children of light,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5.5.</note> and the chil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dren of the day. Further: We ought to giue thanks alway to God for you brethern belooued of the Lord,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.13</note> becauſe that God hath from the beginning choſen you to ſaluation through ſanctification of the Spirit and the faith of trueth. Whence commeth this iudgement and good opinion, yea aſſured<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe that S. Paule had of thoſe to whome hee had preached the Goſpel, but becauſe he ſaw y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tokens of the election in them?<note place="margin">1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.1.</note> And as he ſaith in an other place, that whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they receiued the woord of the preaching of God, they receiued it not as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> woord of men, but as it is in déed the woord of God, which alſo wrought in them that beleeued. Surely cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie (the frute of that faith whiche the holy Apoſtle in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> promiſes of God) mooued him to hope wel of thoſe whiche had wel begon, becauſe God wil performe his woork:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 139.</note> And as touching thoſe, which profited not ſo wel in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> doctrin of the Goſpel as the other which were ſo far ſtrayed that they ſémed wholly out of the way, he is ſo far from dryuing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:2833:16"/>into deſpair, or caſting them of as deſpiſers of Gods good gifts, that he laboreth with all power,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor</hi> 15.34 <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.19<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> to lead the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> again into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> right way: as we haue all redy ſaid of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Corinthians and Galathia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s: to whom he writeth thꝰ. Awake to liue righteouſly &amp; ſin not, for ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e haue not the knowledge of God. And alſo: My little children of whom I trauail in birth again, vntil Chriſt be fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d again in you. Such and like exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ples teach vs rather to prouoke by all menes poſſible, ſuch as are out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> right way to return back again &amp; to commit the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the mercy of God, then to caſt them of as deſperate, or to beſeech God to ouerthrowe and confound them except wee haue ſome certain reuelation as they had of whom we ſpake before. If then any haue abuſed the benefits of God, and namely the knowledge of the Ghoſpel, and afterwarde be ſtricken with the feeling of their ſin, and oppreſſed with the iudgement of God, if they repent and ſéek to reconcile the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Church, let not vs be ſo cruel, as to ſhut vp the entry of the kingdome of Heauen from them, ſée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that the very Angels are more ioyfull for a ſinner that repenteth him,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luc.</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
7.</note> then for nin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tie and nine iuſt men which néed no amend<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of life. Further more before we co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>clude, it is neceſſary that the Readers be admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ed, that in any wiſe they abuſe not that
<pb facs="tcp:2833:16"/>which hath béen ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as if we would giue libertie to ſcoffers &amp; mockers to dally with God, &amp; to forſake the troth as oft as they liſt for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> nature &amp; malice of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſeeketh alwaies theſe wicked extremityes, &amp; neuer kéepeth meaſure in deuine &amp; heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly thingꝭ, but find<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eth alwaies ſomwhat to carp at, &amp; to blame the pure doctrin of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> troth. As: If we declare what y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Scripture teacheth touching electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and reprobation, that is,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ephe.</hi> 1.4. <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.18. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi>
2.14.</note> that God hath choſen ſome, yea before the foundatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the world, to giue them eternall life, and that this election is frée, and that God hath mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy on whome he wil haue mercy, and whom he wil he hardeneth: ſtraight waies the car<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nall &amp; naturall man which comprehendeth not the thingꝭ y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> are of the ſpirit of God, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludeth thervpon, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> we need not to paſſe for wel liuing:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 10, 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> For if I be (ſaith he) predeſtinat to ſaluation &amp; euerlaſting life, I cannot pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, ſéeing y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> the choſen are out of daunger, and contrary wiſe if I be a reprobate, I can not force y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wil of God which hath appoi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted me to perdition: &amp; ſo the fleſh wil take occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to liue at pleaſure, as if y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> end of our electi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on were not, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> we ſhould be holy &amp; without bla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e before him in loue.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ephe.</hi> 1.4. <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.28 <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.5.</note> And if we ſay as the troth is, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> faith iuſtifieth, &amp; that our work ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not ſatiſfy y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of god to obtai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> grace &amp; righteouſnes, yea &amp; whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we haue done all
<pb facs="tcp:2833:17"/>that is commaunded vs to doo, we muſt con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>feſſe our ſelues to be vnprofitable ſeruants, ſtraight waies they cry out that this doctrin is falce and hereticall, that it maketh men careleſſe and ſlouthful to doo good woorks: ſee<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing that if the opinion of merit be taken a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>way, we ſhal neuer doo any thing with good courage. But theſe poore ignorant men or rather Hipocrites, conſider not that when we attribute to faith the meanes of iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.6.</note> we comdemne not good woorks whiche are the effects and frutes therof, ſeeing that a true and liuely faith woorketh by charitie, and that the end of our vocation is,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.4.</note> that we walke in newneſſe of like. For that it is written: Euery frée that bringeth not foorth good frute ſhalbe hewen down and throwen into the fire.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.10.16.</note> Alſo: Let your light ſo ſhine be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore men that they may ſee your good woorkꝭ and glorifie your father which is in heauen. Alſo: If a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> abide not in me, he is caſt forth as a branch,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn.</hi> 15.6.</note> and withereth, and men ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thereth them and caſt them into the fire, and then burn. And S. Paule ſaith: Beloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued bréethern be you ſtedfaſt,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Cor.</hi>
15.58.</note> vnmoouable, abundant alwaies in the woork of the Lord for aſmuch as ye knowe that your labor is not in vain in the Lord.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ephe.</hi> 2.10.</note> And again: We are his woorkmanſhip created in Chriſte Ieſus vnto good woorks which God hath or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayned
<pb facs="tcp:2833:17"/>that we ſhould walke in them. In an other place: Do theſe things (ſaith hee) and the God of peace ſhalbe with you.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Phill</hi> 4.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.14.</note> And ſpeaking of Ieſus Chriſte, he ſaith: Who gaue him ſelf for vs y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hee might redeme vs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all iniquitie &amp; purge vs to be a perticuler people vnto himſelf, zealouſly giuen to good woorks.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.12.</note> S. Péeter alſo writeth after this ſort: Haue your co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerſation honeſt among the Gentles, that they which ſpeake euil of you as of euill dooers, may (by your good woorks which they ſhall ſee) glorify God in the day of the viſitation. To be ſhort, the whole Scripture teacheth vs, to beſtowe the time of our whole life in dooing good woorks,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſay.</hi> 61.3. 1. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4 7.
<hi>Ephe.</hi> 2.8. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.18</note> ſéeing that we are like trees plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, to glorify God, and that he hath not cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led vs to vncleanneſſe, but vnto holineſſe. And neuertheleſſe the ſame Scripture ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withall teacheth vs, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> we are ſaued by grace through faith, and that not of our ſelues, for it is the gift of God: not through woorks, leſt any man ſhould boaſt him ſelf. For I count that the afflictions of this preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t time are not worthy of the glory whiche ſhalbe ſhewed vnto vs.</p>
            <p>And euen as of theſe two former points man goeth about to conclude and malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly to gather, that it is in vain to endeuer to walke in holyneſſe of life: ſo likewiſe. I
<pb facs="tcp:2833:18"/>knowe that ſome may ſo take the contents of this treatiſe, touching the repentance of ſinners, as if we would qualify the ſin of thoſe, which after knowledge of the truth of the goſpel, ſtick not ſhamefully to ronounce and forſake the ſame, either vnder pretence of wekeneſſe, or fear of men, or torments, or loſſe of goods, or honors of this world, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other cauſe what ſo euer it be. But when we go about to bring again thoſe that are gone aſtray, into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> right way of ſaluation, it is not to giue occaſion to others to ſtray out of the way. When we teach thoſe that ar ſick, or hurt, a méet remedy to heal them, it is not to cauſe ſuch as are whole to giue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e deadly wound, to ſee if y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reme<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy which we taught y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other wil help them.</p>
            <p>When we receiue the ſtrayed ſhéep into the flock of Chriſte, it is not to make the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther which were there long before to depart out, and to ſay that they wil come into the flock again as oft as they liſt. Again, when we ſet foorth to the ſinner what ſo euer hee be, the blood of Ieſus Chriſte wich is ready to clenſe his conſcience from the woorks of death, to ſerue the liuing God, it is not to giue any occaſion to abuſe the ſame,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.28.</note> or to tread it vnder feet. For he that deſpiſeth Mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſes law, dieth without mercy vnder two or three witneſſes. Of how much ſorer puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb facs="tcp:2833:18"/>ſuppoſe ye ſhall he be worthy, whiche treadeth vnder foot the Sonne of God, and counteth the blood of the Teſtament as an vnholy thing, wherwith he was ſanctified, and dooth deſpite the ſpirit of grace?</p>
            <p>To the end then that none flatter them ſelues, as if it were a light thing to dally with God,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.18.</note> and to withholde his trueth in vnrighteouſnes, let all men vnderſtand, that the mercy of God is ſo offred vnto ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke.</hi> 4.18.</note> that none but the broken harted re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue it. Th'other which are hardned &amp; obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, and deſpiſe the riches of his bountiful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and patience and long ſuffering, doo but heap wrath vnto them ſelues againſt the day of wrath,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.4.5</note> and of the declaration of the iuſt iudgement of God, who wil rewarde e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery man according to his woorks, but eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially thoſe that of determinat malice &amp; cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed obſtinacye abuſe the knowledge of the Goſpel, &amp; deny the Lord which hath bought them, and are cauſe that the name of God is blaſphemed of the wicked, and the way of troth blamed.<note place="margin">2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.20</note> For if after they haue with drawen them ſelues from the filthynes of death, through the knowledge of the Lorde and Sauioure Ieſus Chriſte, they be ouer come and wrapped again therein, their la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter eſtate is wurſe then their firſt. For it had béen better neuer to haue knowen the
<pb facs="tcp:2833:19"/>way of Iuſtice, then after the knoweledge thereof, to turn back again from the holy commandement which was giuen them.</p>
            <p>But the common prouerbe is verified in them.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 26.11.</note> The Dog is returned again to his vo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mit, and the waſhed Sow, returned again to her wallowing in the mire. Let them the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to whom God hath giuen the grace to know Ieſus Chriſte his woord, ſéek for their ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation in fear and trembling. And let him that thinketh him ſelf to ſtand,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil</hi> 2.12. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.12</note> take héed he fall not. And to this end let vs haue all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies theſe ſentences before our eyes, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che pronounce horrible vengeance on the mockers and deſpiſers of the Goſpel, which wickedly &amp; vnthankfully miſuſe the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge that they haue recieued of the troth of God. Let vs remember that it is not writ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ten in vain:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.33.</note> He that denyeth mee before men, I wil alſo deny him before my father which is heauen.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi>
8.38.</note> Alſo: Whoſoeuer ſhall be aſhamed of me and of my woords among this adulterous and ſinful generatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, of him ſhall the Sonne of man bee aſhamed alſo, when he commeth in the glory of his father with the holy Angels. Further: He that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>léeueth in the Sonne hath euerlaſting life,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn.</hi> 3.36.</note> and he that obeyeth not the Sonne, ſhal not ſee life, but the wrath of god abideth on him.</p>
            <p>The holy Ghoſt by the mouth of S. Iohn
<pb facs="tcp:2833:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>alſo accuſeth the father and mother of him that was borne blinde, of their fearfulnes that durſt not openly confeſſe that Ieſus Chriſt had opened their Sonnes eyes:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 9.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> for they feared the Iewes, that had all redy or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayned, that if any man did confeſſe that he was the Chriſte, he ſhould be exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municate out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Sinagog He approoueth of like cow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ardnes and fainthartednes, many of the chéef of the Iewes, whiche beleeued in Ieſus Chriſte, and confeſſed him not becauſe of the Phariſeis, for fear they ſhuld thruſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out of the Sinagog. For they looued (ſaith he) the glory of men, more then the glory of God.<note place="margin">2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.12</note> Alſo S. Paule writeth of the Lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus: If we deny him he alſo wil deny vs, if we beléeue not yet abideth he faithful, hee cannot deny him ſelf. And the Author of the Epiſtle to the Hebrues, ſheweth euidently among other things, what horrible ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance is prepared for thoſe that deſpiſe the troth that is declared vnto them:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.2.</note> If the woord (ſaith he) ſpoken by Angels was ſted<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>faſt, and euery tranſgreſſion &amp; diſobedience receiued a iuſt recompence of reward, how ſhall we eſcape, if we neglect ſo great ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? And again:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.31. <hi>&amp;.</hi> 12 16.17.</note> It is a fearfull thing to fall into the hands of the liuing God. Alſo: Let there be no fornicator or prophane per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, as
<hi>Eſau,</hi> whiche for a porcion of meat
<pb facs="tcp:2833:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſolde his birthright, for ye knowe how that afterward alſo when he would haue inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rited the bleſſing he was reiected, for he fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d no place of repentance, though he ſought the bleſſing with teares. Finally it is ſaid, that the fearful and vnbeléeuing ſhall haue their parte in the lake that burneth with fire and brimſtone,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Apoc.</hi> 21.8 2. <hi>Cor</hi> 6.1. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi>
1.17.</note> which is the ſecond death. Theſe and ſuch like ſentences admoniſh vs not to receiue the grace of God in vaine, but to paſſe the time of our dwelling héer in fear. Neuertheleſſe none of theſe are contrary to the doctrin whiche wee haue before taught, that is that we ought not raſhly to iudge of that whiche God wil haue hidden from vs, nor reiect thoſe which for a time fall of from the trueth knowen, but rather allure them to repentance,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.1.</note> and if they repent, to receiue them in the ſpirit of méekneſſe: yea though they doo but ſéem to repent, let vs not leaue to ſhew the duty of charitie vnto them, wai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting til God (whiche is the ſearcher of the hart) diſcloſe the wickednes and Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie of thoſe which vnder coulour of fay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned holines, would gladly begile bothe God and men.</p>
            <p>To conclude let vs threaten the rebelles and wicked deſpiſers of Gods iudgements, that on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other ſide we giue occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to none to diſpair of ſaluation.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſa.</hi> 104.35</note> Let vs ſo wiſh with
<pb facs="tcp:2833:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>Dauid that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſinners may be conſumed out of the Earth, til therbe no more wicked,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſa.</hi> 53.7.</note> that we forget not that which an other Prophet ſaith: Let the wicked forſake his waies, and the vnrighteous his owne imaginations re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>turn vnto the Lord, &amp; he wil haue mercy vp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on him, and to our God, for he is very redy to forgiue. To him be glory, dominion and honor now and for euer. Amen.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ephe</hi>
                  <hi>Yea euen vnto him that is able to doo exceeding abundantly,</hi> 3.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 2. <hi>Pet.</hi>
3.18.</note> 
               <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue all that we aſke or think, to him, I ſay, be glory, now and for euer world without end. Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>¶ <hi>Laus Deo.</hi>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>¶ <hi>Imprinted at London by Iohn</hi> Allde, for Lucas Hariſon dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling <hi>in Paules Church yard at the</hi> ſigne of the Crane.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:2833:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2833:21"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
